Cristóbal Sifón

Profesor Auxiliar Instituto de Física, Facultad de Ciencias Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso Casilla 4059, Valparaíso, Chile

E-mail: cristobal.sifon@pucv.cl Phone: +56 (32) 227 4698

https://github.com/cristobal-sifon/

Research Interests

My research focuses on galaxy cluster physics including observable—mass scaling relations for cosmological analyses and the transformation of galaxies in and around galaxy clusters. I am also interested in intrinsic galaxy alignments, both as contaminants for cosmic shear and as a physical mechanism in their own right. I use various tools and techniques to study these phenomena, including weak gravitational lensing, spectroscopy, the exploitation of optical surveys in general, and most recently also of hydrodynamical simulations.

Collaborations: 4MOST Chilean Cluster Galaxy Evolution Survey (CHANCES) — 4MOST Hemisphere Survey (4HS) — Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) — Canadian Cluster Comparison Project (CCCP) — Cerro Chajnator Atacama Telescope (CCAT) — CMB-S4 — Galaxy Cluster Mass Reconstruction Project — Kilo-Degree Survey (KiDS) — Legacy Survey of Space and Time Dark Energy Science Collaboration (LSST-DESC) — Multi-Epoch Nearby Cluster Survey (MENeaCS) — Simons Observatory.

Employment

[2022 - Present] Profesor Auxiliar, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Chile

[2019 - 2022] Profesor Asociado, PUCV

[2016 - 2019] Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University, USA

Education

[2012 - 2016] Ph.D. Astrophysics, Universiteit Leiden, The Netherlands

[2010 - 2012] M.Sc. Astrophysics, P. Universidad Católica de Chile (PUC), Chile

[2005 - 2010] B.Sc. Astronomy, PUC

Teaching & Mentoring

Graduate Research Mentoring

[2023 - Present] Javier Urrutia, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2020 - 2022] Camila Aros, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2017 – 2019] Naomi Robertson, Oxford University (UK): co-advised PhD thesis project (Advisor: Joanna Dunkley).

[2013 – 2014] Joshua Albert, Universiteit Leiden: co-advised MSc thesis project (Advisor: Huub Röttgering).

Undergraduate Research Mentoring

[PUCV] 3 Senior theses and 4 Summer projects.

[Princeton] Summer project and Junior project.

[Others] Four-month research project through the Central American-Caribbean Bridge in Astrophysics (URL).

Courses Taught

Graduate: Data Analysis (2023), Techniques of Observational Astrophysics (2022), Observational Cosmology (2020-2021)

Undergraduate: Astronomical Instrumentation (2023), Galactic Astronomy (2021-2022), Programming (2020-

2022), Cosmology (2020)

Non-Physics Major: Basic Astronomy for Engineers (2022)

Grants

[2020] ALMA-ANID Fund to hire a postdoc (Co-PI, 2 years, US\$77,000) [2019] FONDECYT Iniciación research grant (PI, 3 years, US\$125,000)

Successful Observing Proposals (as PI)

I have been the PI of 12 successful observing proposals totalling hundreds of observing hours in optical (Gemini-South/GMOS, VST/OmegaCAM), near-infrared (Magellan/Fourstar), submm (APEX/CONCERTO), and radio (GMRT, VLA) telescopes.

Observing Experience: I have spent roughly 180 hours observing with optical (Gemini South/GMOS) and near-infrared (NTT/Sofl, Magellan/Fourstar) instruments performing both imaging and spectroscopy of galaxy clusters.

Community Activity

Journals: I have served as a referee for Astronomy & Astrophysics, The Astrophysical Journal, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, and Nature Astronomy.

Telescope Allocation Committees: Canadian Astronomical Society, Chandra X-ray Observatory

Grant Allocation Committees: Swiss National Science Foundation

Press Articles Authored

[July 2017] Galaxy clusters: Falling into line (Nature Astronomy News & Views)

[July 2013] Featured Science: Dynamical masses of galaxy clusters discovered with the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (Gemini Focus)

Outreach

[Nov. 2023] Guest in "Diálogos Cósmicos" podcast (in Spanish, available here).

[Aug. 2023] Guest in "Conversemos de Astronomía" podcast (in Spanish, available here).

[Nov. 2022] Guest in "Rockstars" podcast by Radio TXS (in Spanish, available here).

[Oct. 2022] Interview for Radio Valentín Letelier, Valparaíso, to talk about CHANCES.

[Mar. 2021] Online public talk in the conext of the Chilean Day of Astronomy (in Spanish, available here).

[2018 - 2019] Assisted with Public Astronomical Observations in Spanish, Princeton University.

[2013 - 2014] Assisted with Public Observations at the Old Observatory, Leiden Observatory.

[2012] Co-taught an Astronomy Course for Seniors, PUC.

[2011] Participated in *Starry Nights*, observation nights for elementary and middle school students in social risk organized by ESO-Santiago.

[2010] Invited talk on board the "FFG14 Almirante Latorre" Chilean Navy ship, Valparaíso, Chile.

[2010] The Universe, a series of talks for elementary school students in social risk organized by PUC.

Technical skills

I am an experienced Python programmer and I have some familiarity with IDL and Julia. I wrote pygmos, a Python/PyRAF pipeline to reduce Gemini-GMOS spectra which is available here. I am one of the lead developers and maintainers of the galaxy-galaxy lensing pipeline used by the KiDS collaboration (written in Python, but which is not public at the moment). Other codes I have written are posted at my github page.

Other Work Experience

[2020 - 2021] Data science & Machine Learning2 consultant, Minera Centinela, Chile.

[2007 – 2008] Ski instructor at Homewood Mountain Ski Resort in Lake Tahoe, CA, USA. Obtained certification as *Level I Ski Instructor* by the Professional Ski Instructors of America (PSIA).

[2006 - 2007] Ski lift operator at Sun Valley Resort, Sun Valley, ID, USA.

References

Prof. Henk Hoekstra (PhD advisor)
 Leiden Observatory, Universiteit Leiden
 Niels Bohrweg 2, NL-2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands

Phone: +31 (71) 527 5594

E-mail: hoekstra@strw.leidenuniv.nl

Prof. John P. Hughes
 Department of Physics and Astronomy, Rutgers University
 136 Frelinghuysen Rd., Piscataway, NJ 08854, USA

Phone: +1 (848) 445 8878

E-mail: jph@physics.rutgers.edu

• Prof. Felipe Menanteau

Department of Astronomy, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 1002 W. Green St., Urbana, IL 61801, USA

Phone: +1 (217) 244 6297 E-mail: felipe@illinois.edu

• Prof. David N. Spergel

Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute 160 Fifth Avenue, 7th Floor, New York, NY 10010, USA

Phone: +1 (646) 654 0066

E-mail: dns@astro.princeton.edu

Prof. L. Felipe Barrientos (MSc advisor)
 Instituto de Astrofísica, P. Universidad Católica de Chile
 Casilla 306, Santiago 22, Chile

Phone: +56 (2) 2354 4941

E-mail: barrientos@astro.uc.cl

Publication list

I have co-authored 131 scientific articles intended for peer-reviewed publication, including 7 first-author papers. They have been cited more than 7,000 times and have an h-index of 46, with more than 350 citations on my first-author papers. The full list of publications can be accessed at the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System. This document is maintained live on github.

First-Author Papers

- 8. C. Sifón, J. Han, "The history and mass content of cluster galaxies in the EAGLE simulation", 2023, Draft, to be submitted to A&A
- C. Sifón, R. Herbonnet, H. Hoekstra, R. F. J. van der Burg, M. Viola, "The Galaxy-Subhalo Connection in Low-Redshift Galaxy Clusters from Weak Gravitational Lensing", 2018, MNRAS, 478, 1244
 [arXiv]
- C. Sifón, R. F. J. van der Burg, H. Hoekstra, A. Muzzin, R. Herbonnet, "A First Constraint on the Average Mass of Ultra Diffuse Galaxies from Weak Gravitational Lensing", 2018, MNRAS, 473, 3747 [arXiv]
- 5. C. Sifón et al. (25 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Dynamical Masses for 44 SZ-Selected Galaxy Clusters over 755 Square Degrees", 2016, MNRAS, 461, 248 [arXiv]
- 4. C. Sifón et al. (26 co-authors), "The Masses of Satellites in GAMA Galaxy Groups from 100 Square Degrees of KiDS Weak Lensing Data", 2015, MNRAS, 454, 3938 [arXiv]
- 3. C. Sifón, H. Hoekstra, M. Cacciato, M. Viola, F. Köhlinger, R. F. J. van der Burg, D. J. Sand, M. L. Graham, "Constraints on the Alignments of Galaxies in Galaxy Clusters from ~14,000 Spectroscopic Members", 2015, A&A, 575, A48 [arXiv]
- 2. C. Sifón, F. Menanteau, J. P. Hughes, M. Carrasco, L. F. Barrientos, "Strong Lensing Analysis of PLCK G004.5–19.5, a Planck-Discovered Cluster Hosting a Radio Relic at z=0.52", 2014, A&A, 562, A43 [arXiv]
- 1. C. Sifón et al. (36 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Dynamical Masses and Scaling Relations for a Sample of Massive Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect Selected Galaxy Clusters", 2013, ApJ, 772, 25 [arXiv]

Major Contributor Papers

- 16. N. C. Robertson, C. Sifón, et al. (23 co-authors), "ACT-DR5 Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Clusters: Weak Lensing Mass Calibration with KiDS", 2023, arXiv:2304.10219, accepted for publication in A&A
- 15. A. Dolfi, F. A. Gómez, A. Monachesi, S. Varela-Lavín, P. B. Tissera, C. Sifón, G. Galaz, "Lopsidedness As a Tracer of Early Galactic Assembly History", 2023, MNRAS, 526, 567 [arXiv]
- 14. M. Hilton, C. Sifón, et al. (133 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: a Catalog of >4000 Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Galaxy Clusters", 2021, ApJS, 253, 3 [arXiv]
- 13. M. S. Madhavacheril, C. Sifón, et al. (61 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Weighing Distant Clusters with the Most Ancient Light", 2020, ApJL, 903, 13 [arXiv]
- R. Herbonnet, C. Sifón, H. Hoekstra, Y. Bahé, R. F. J. van der Burg, J.-B. Melin, A. von der Linden, D. Sand, S. Kay, D. Barnes, "CCCP and MENeaCS: (Updated) Weak-Lensing Masses for 100 Galaxy Clusters", 2020, MNRAS, 497, 4684 [arXiv]

- 11. M. Hilton, M. Hasselfield, C. Sifón, et al. (43 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: The Two-Season ACTPol Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect Selected Cluster Catalog", 2018, ApJS, 235, 20 [arXiv]
- 10. J. G. Albert, C. Sifón, A. Stroe, F. Mernier, H. T. Intema, H. J. A. Röttgering, G. Brunetti, "Complex Diffuse Emission in the z=0.52 Cluster PLCK G004.5–19.5", 2017, A&A, 607, A4 [arXiv]
- 9. R. F. J. van der Burg, H. Hoekstra, A. Muzzin, C. Sifón, et al. (17 co-authors), "The Abundance of Ultra-Diffuse Galaxies from Groups to Clusters: UDGs Are Relatively More Common in More Massive Haloes", 2017, A&A, 607, A79 [arXiv]
- 8. E. van Uitert, M. Cacciato, H. Hoekstra, M. Brouwer, C. Sifón, et al. (29 co-authors), "The Stellar-to-Halo Mass Relation of GAMA Galaxies from 100 Square Degrees of KiDS Weak Lensing Data", 2016, MNRAS, 459, 3251 [arXiv]
- 7. D. Kirk, M. L. Brown, H. Hoekstra, B. Joachimi, T. D. Kitching, R. Mandelbaum, C. Sifón, M. Cacciato, A. Choi, A. Kiessling, A. Leonard, A. Rassat, B. Malte Schäfer, "Galaxy Alignments: Observations and Impact on Cosmology", 2015, Space Sci. Rev., 193, 139 [arXiv]
- A. Kiessling, M. Cacciato, B. Joachimi, D. Kirk, T. D. Kitching, A. Leonard, R. Mandelbaum, B. Malte Schäfer, C. Sifón, M. L. Brown, A. Rassat, "Galaxy Alignments: Theory, Modelling & Simulations", 2015, Space Sci. Rev., 193, 67 [arXiv]
- 5. B. Joachimi, M. Cacciato, T. D. Kitching, A. Leonard, R. Mandelbaum, B. Malte Schäfer, C. Sifón, H. Hoekstra, A. Kiessling, D. Kirk, A. Rassat, "Galaxy Alignments: an Overview", 2015, Space Sci. Rev., 193, 1 [arXiv]
- 4. R. F. J. van der Burg, H. Hoekstra, A. Muzzin, C. Sifón, M. L. Balogh, S. McGee, "Evidence for the Inside-Out Growth of the Stellar Mass Distribution in Galaxy Clusters since $z\sim 1$ ", 2015, A&A, 577, 19 [arXiv]
- 3. M. Hilton, M. Hasselfield, C. Sifón, et al. (26 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: The Stellar Content of Galaxy Clusters Selected Using the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect", 2013, MNRAS, 435, 3469 [arXiv]
- F. Menanteau, C. Sifón, et al. (26 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Physical Properties of Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect Clusters on the Celestial Equator", 2013, ApJ, 765, 67 [arXiv]
- 1. F. Menanteau, J. P. Hughes, C. Sifón, et al. (27 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: ACT-CL J0102-4915 "El Gordo," a Massive Merging Cluster at Redshift 0.87", 2012, ApJ, 748, 7 [arXiv]

Selected Recent Contributing Author Papers (All including C. Sifón)

- 10. J. van Marrewijk et al. (20 co-authors), "XLSSC 122 Caught in the Act of Growing Up: Spatially Resolved SZ Observations of a z=1.98 Galaxy Cluster", 2023, arXiv:2310.17535, submitted to A&A
- Dark Energy Survey and Kilo-Degree Survey Collaborations et al. (162 co-authors), "DES Y3 + KiDS-1000: Consistent Cosmology Combining Cosmic Shear Surveys", 2023, The Open Journal of Astrophysics, 6, 36
- 8. W. Coulton et al. (154 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: High-Resolution Component-Separated Maps Across One-Third of the Sky", 2023, arXiv:2307.01258, submitted to Phys. Rev. D

- 7. B. L. Frye et al. (44 co-authors), "The JWST PEARLS View of the El Gordo Galaxy Cluster and of the Structure It Magnifies", 2023, ApJ, 952, 81 [arXiv]
- G. A. Marques et al. (97 co-authors), "Cosmological Constraints from the Tomography of DES-Y3
 Galaxies with CMB Lensing from ACT DR4", 2023, arXiv:2306.17268, accepted for publication in
 JCAP
- M. S. Madhavacheril et al. (159 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: DR6 Gravitational Lensing Map and Cosmological Parameters", 2023, arXiv:2304.05203, accepted for publication in ApJ
- 4. F. J. Qu et al. (158 co-authors), "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: a Measurement of the DR6 CMB Lensing Power Spectrum and Its Implications for Structure Growth", 2023, arXiv:2304.05202, accepted for publication in ApJ
- 3. C. Haines et al. (20 co-authors), "CHANCES: A CHileAN Cluster galaxy Evolution Survey", 2023, The Messenger, 190, 31
- 2. J. E. Greene, J. P. Greco, A. D. Goulding, S. Huang, E. Kado-Fong, S. Danieli, J. Li, J. H. Kim, Y. Komiyama, A. Leauthaud, L. A. Macarthur, C. Sifón, "The Nature of Low-Surface-Brightness Galaxies in the Hyper Suprime-Cam Survey", 2022, ApJ, 933, 150 [arXiv]
- M. Aguena et al. (24 co-authors), "CLMM: a LSST-DESC Cluster Weak Lensing Mass Modeling Library for Cosmology", 2021, MNRAS, 508, 6092 [arXiv]